前情提要
歡迎來到魔多
Welcome to Mordor.
願意發誓效忠阿達爾嗎
Do you swear allegiance to Adar?
我們沒什麼好怕的了
There is no one left for us to fear.
還有一個 一名遠古妖術師
There is one. An ancient sorcerer.
放了我的子民 我就告訴你那名妖術師在哪裏
Set my people free, and I will tell you where he can be found.
你就能消滅他
So you can destroy him.
母親...
Mother. Mother.
有座火山蘇醒了
A fire-mountain awoke. -
隨之產生的地動山搖 卻沿着大地之骨一路蔓延過來
The ground-shakes it produced spread through the bones of the earth,
摧毀了我們的礦井
collapsing our sun-shafts.
黑暗之手已包覆卡扎督姆
The hand of darkness has closed around Khazad-d?m.
我們聽不到山的聲音了
We can't hear the mountains anymore.
此時此刻整個中洲正岌岌可危
At this very moment, all Middle-earth balances on the brink of the abyss.
力量之戒是我們重返光明的最後機會
And the Rings of Power are our last hope of restoring the light.
這是某種邀請...
It's some sort of invitation...
來自凱勒布林博大人
from Lord Celebrimbor.
努門諾爾島國
The Island Kingdom of Númenor.
這裏曾經有七顆真知晶石
Seven Seeing Stones there once were.
這一顆傳到我父王手上
This one was passed to my father.
有誰願意承擔保護攝政女王的責任
Who is willing to commit themselves to our Queen-regent's protection?
我願意效力
I will serve.
–我願意效力  –我願意效力
- I will serve! - I will serve!
–法拉宗  –跟我來
Pharaz?n! Come with me.
他爲什麼不阻止這件事
Why didn't he stop this?
–他對她很忠誠 無論對或... –錯
- He's loyal to her. Rightly or... - Wrongly.
你堂姐手握權杖 但人民追隨的是你
Your cousin may hold the scepter, but it's you the people follow.
–有他們支持 你可以... –可以怎樣
With their help you could... Could what?
發揮你的影響力
Assert your influence.
–找掩護  –女王
- Take shelter! - The Queen!
不要
No!
伊熙爾杜
Isildur!
我兒子呢
Where is my son?
怎麼回事
What is it?
你看到什麼
What do you see?
指環王:力量之戒
第二季第三集
本WEB版外掛字幕由  風吹來的那片雲  雙語合併
我來吧
Give him to me.
不行
No!
乖乖回家 聽到沒
You're going home. Do you hear me?
跟我們回家
You're coming with us.
別這樣 貝雷克
Please, Berek.
–拜託了 –它不會聽你的話
Please. He won't listen to you.
它不會聽我們任何人的話
He won't listen to any of us.
別害怕 四條腿的
Don't be afraid, four-legs.
我們不會吃了你 暫時不會
We ain't gonna eat ya... yet.
逮到你啦
Yeah, got ya.
別想跑
No. Not yet.
來啊
Come on!
–跑掉了 快追啊  –算了 讓它去吧
- No! It's getting away! After it! - No! Let him go.
前面是暗黑森林
That there's the Black Forest.
沒東西能活着出來
Nothin' comes outta there alive.
貝雷克
Berek.
好小子
My boy.
貝雷克 走
Berek, go!
快
Go!
努門諾爾
國王始終保護着忠貞派 我會想念他的
As king he always protected The Faithful. I shall miss him.
你侃侃而談死去的國王
You speak so freely of dead kings,
卻不願提及你兒子的名字
yet you refuse to utter your own son's name.
你真的不需自責 該責怪的另有其人
You blame yourself but you needn't. True blame belongs to another.
你到底想說什麼
What is it you're trying to say?
聽好了 我們島國就要滅亡了 還有時間...
So know this, our island will fall, and there is still time...
怎麼了
What is it?
攝政女王
Queen-regent.
船長
Captain.
你看到什麼
What do you see?
北方的貴族來了
The nobles from the North are here.
貝爾札加爾大人看來是來致敬的
It seems Lord Belzagar has come to pay his respects.
沒敬意的人是無法致敬的
One cannot pay what one does not have.
他聽信法拉宗 還是反過來
Does Pharaz?n have his ear or is it the other way around?
後者
The latter.
攝政女王
Queen-regent?
我們就這樣回報逝去之人嗎
Is this how we repay our fallen?
–這只是開始... –不
- It is only the beginning of our-- - No!
慢着...
Wait! [panting] Wait.
告訴我
Tell me.
你失去了什麼人
Who is it you lost?
我的兒子
My son.
你父親的遺物
- Your father's effects? - Oh.
我沒聽到你進來
I didn't hear you come in.
死者的遺物
Possessions of the dead.
將成爲神聖的鑰匙 能打開永遠緊閉的大門
They become hallowed keys into doors that are, now, forever shut.
我記得我父親去世的時候
I remember when my father died.
我盯着一個杯子看 裏面是他前一晚喝剩一半的酒
Looking at a cup, half-filled with wine he'd drunk the night before.
把酒倒掉感覺像是種背叛
It seemed a betrayal to empty the glass,
但他也討厭浪費好酒
but he also hated wasting good wine.
所以我喝掉了
So, I drank it.
你來做什麼
Why are you here?
讓我看看你藏在背後的東西 我就告訴你
Show me what you hide behind your back, and I will tell you.
沒什麼 堂弟
Nothing, cousin.
你該做出選擇了
But it is time for you to choose.
你的禮服
Your gown.
要深紅色 代表努門諾爾的未來 還是白色 代表過去
Crimson, for Númenor's future, or white, her past?
是什麼場合
What is the occasion?
你的加冕大典
Your coronation.
我們哀悼死者夠久了
We have mourned the dead long enough.
也該關心一下生者了
It is time that we attend to the concerns of the living.
我父親當年選擇白色
My father wore white.
我只記得這個
That's all I can recall.
還有大鷹
That, and an eagle.
用大鷹來裝飾加冕大典很罕見
It is rare for an eagle to grace a coronation.
如果有隻大鷹出現在加冕大典上 會被視爲吉兆
Should one make an appearance at yours, it would be seen as an auspicious omen.
那就白色吧
The white, then.
我偏愛紅色
I'm partial to the red.
“如同太陽 新的君主冉冉升起”
"Like the sun, rises a new monarch."
能向人民展示 你是新時代新形態的統治者
It will show the people you're a new kind of ruler for a new day.
人民需要改變
They need change.
還是白色吧 比較謙遜
The white. It is humbler.
悉聽尊便
As you prefer.
她跟她父親一樣 永遠不知變通
She's the same as her father, she's never going to change.
她身體有恙 不再適合治國了
She's suffered an infirmity. She's no longer fit to rule.
笑什麼 這是事實
Why laugh? It's the truth.
醉話而已 醉了還是別大聲嚷嚷比較好
It is the ale talking. It would be wise to lower its voice.
話雖如此 這孩子沒說錯
All the same, the boy's not wrong.
你差點就被選中代替她掌權
You were nearly chosen to rule in her stead.
這片土地仍有多數人認爲 你是更好的選擇
Much of this land still believes that yours was the better claim.
在彌瑞爾的好戰之舉後 多數人準備再次提出質疑
And after Míriel's warmongering, many are ready to raise it again.
“多數人”是不足以推翻女王的
"Many" is hardly enough to supplant a Queen.
攝政女王
Queen-regent.
一介盲目之人
A blind one.
要是有人知道怎麼把 “多數人”變成“夠多人”呢
What if someone knew a way to turn "many" into "enough"?
既然知道 爲什麼不說出來呢
In the event that someone did, why would they not bring it forth?
可能害怕後果吧
They might be afraid of what could happen.
這張桌子上沒什麼好怕的 孩子
There is nothing to fear at this table, my child.
埃雅瑞恩
E?rien?
果然是你
Thought that was you.
維藍迪爾
Valandil.
我以爲公會的人
You know, I thought Guilds-folk preferred
偏愛待在更時尚的地方呢
to keep to the more fashionable part of town.
你們來舊城區幹嘛
What are you doing in the Old Quarter?
來安葬國王
We came here to bury a king.
願維拉讓他安息並守護他
The Valar rest him and keep him.
真希望我能在場
I should've liked to have been there.
可惜一般士兵沒有受邀
Pity members of the common soldiery weren't invited.
尤其考慮到那些底層民衆
Especially given the low class of folk that were.
你剛是在羞辱我父親嗎
Did you just insult my father?
我是在羞辱你
No, I believe I insulted you.
我跟女王一同上戰場灑熱血
I bled with the Queen on the battlefield.
親眼看着她衝進地獄裏救人
I watched her walk into an inferno to save lives.
試圖拯救她哥哥的性命
To try and save her brother's life.
再敢說女王的不是 身體有恙的就會是你們
You speak ill of the Queen again, it'll be you, suffers an infirmity.
我說得夠清楚嗎
Have I made myself plain?
還是要用其他方式解決
Or need we settle this through other means?
今天夠清楚了
Plain enough for today.
看來需要再來一杯
Well, I'd say that's worth another ale.
埃雅瑞恩 你剛講到哪裏
What was it you were about to say, E?rien?
我發現某個東西...
I found something...
天大祕密
Something secret.
相當危險
Something dangerous.
禁忌之物
Something forbidden.
領主大人 準備工作就快完成了
The preparations are nearly complete, Lord-father.
只是...我們在這裏很安全
But... we are safe here.
有自己的家
We have a home.
有必要再次開戰嗎
Must we go to war again?
你說索隆已經死了 那就當他死了吧
You told me Sauron was dead. Let us leave him that way.
身爲父親有責任瞭解世上的危險
There are some dangers in this world about which it is a father's burden to know.
孩子有責任相信父親
And a son's burden to trust him.
相信我 孩子
Trust me, my son,
除非確定索隆徹底消失
when I tell you that we will never truly be safe,
我們永遠不會真正安全
until we've made certain Sauron is no more.
遵命 領主大人
As you will it, Lord-father.
滾開
Be off, will ya?
戴莫德 灰色山脈山嶺食人妖
Damrod. Hill-troll of the Ered Mithrin.
石巨人殺手
Killer of stone giants.
龍骨掠食者
Eater of Dragon bones.
歡迎
Welcome.
看來你收到我們的訊息了
I gather you received our message.
索隆在哪
Where is Sauron?
歡迎 謝謝你們專程前來
Welcome. Thank you for making the journey.
在這裏你無需隱藏你的煩惱
You need not hide your troubles here.
我們無意加以利用
We have no intention to take advantage of them,
單純只想提供幫助
simply, to, to render aid.
如同你們曾經幫助過我們
As you once did us.
你認爲你能提供什麼樣的幫助
And exactly what aid do you think you could provide?
戒指
Rings.
中洲 強大無比的矮人諸王各持一隻
One for each of Middle-earth's most powerful Dwarf-lords.
你找我們來就爲了交易珠寶
You brought us here to barter jewelry?
這些戒指的力量 將超越矮人 人類或精靈
These Rings will be beyond any power yet devised
所能生成的任何力量
by Dwarf, or Man, or Elf.
這些戒指將是力量之戒
They shall be Rings of Power.
足以治癒你們的山脈
Power to heal your mountain.
如同治癒了我們的聖樹
Just as they have healed our Great Tree.
埃爾隆德...
Elrond...
祕銀
The mithril?
祕銀扭轉了我們的命運
Mithril has reversed our fortunes.
相信也能扭轉你們的命運
I believe it can do the same for yours.
甚至整個中洲所有種族的命運
Perhaps, for all the peoples of Middle-earth.
我們只要穩定提供祕銀就好了嗎
If we provide you with a steady supply, is that the sum of it?
祕銀 用來打造戒指 沒錯
Mithril, for Rings. Yes.
凱勒布林博大人 這提議太慷慨了
A generous offer, Lord Celebrimbor,
但爲何不直接找我們國王呢
but why not take it to our King?
老都林國王對於接受外援
For Durin the Elder has always been hesitant
一向有所猶豫
to accept outside aid.
但如果我們的提議由他自己人
But if our proposal was brought to him instead
提出來...
by one of his own...
我和我父親已經不再交談了
My father and I are no longer on speaking terms.
都林的意思是...
What Durin means--
要我們兩個共處一室
You'd sooner convince an Orc
還不如叫半獸人去曬太陽還比較快
to sit for a sun-bath, than get the two of us in a room together.
我恐怕是幫不上忙
I'm afraid, I'd be of little help.
我們找你來是要幫助你
We summoned you here to help you.
爲你父親獻上拯救王國的方法
Bringing your father a means of saving his kingdom
或許正好能贏回他對你的尊重
might be just the way to earn back his respect.
甚至你的繼承資格
Perhaps, even your inheritance.
不好意思 請問你哪位
I'm sorry, who exactly are you?
原諒我的疏忽 這位是...
Yes, forgive me. This is--
一個朋友 精靈的朋友
A friend. To the Elves.
也是矮人的朋友 如此而已
And to the Dwarves. Nothing more.
這樣啊 埃爾隆德在哪裏
I see. And where's Elrond?
修復林頓需要他全神貫注
Lindon's restoration demands his full attention.
現在嗎
Does it now?
我保證埃爾隆德傳令官一心掛念着
I assure you, Herald Elrond said he could think of little else
要幫助他的矮人朋友
than helping his Dwarven friends.
他提起你時很關心
He speaks of you so fondly.
妙了
Funny.
他從沒提起過你 這位...
He's never mentioned you. Lord...
安那塔
Annatar.
埃爾隆德說你是矮人族中 最有智慧的一個
Elrond said that you were the wisest of all the Dwarves.
他說的是真的 還是我們應該找其他人談
Did he speak true, or is there someone else we should be treating with?
兩位大人 你們的提議需要深思
My Lords, you've given us much to consider.
能不能給我們一點時間考慮一下
Might we have a wee moment to, uh, to mull it over?
–我們恐怕... –當然了
I am afraid we-- Certainly!
慢慢考慮
Take whatever time you need.
你在想什麼 是想找人吵架嗎
What were you thinking? Were you trying to pick a fight?
我在想 不管那個安那塔是誰
I was thinking, whoever that Annatar is,
他跟埃爾隆德一點也不熟
he doesn't know Elrond from a hole in the ground.
你怎麼知道
How do you know?
因爲埃爾隆德 不可能把我說得那麼好聽
'Cause Elrond would never say such nice things about me.
你一點都不心動嗎
Aren't you in the least bit relieved?
是啦 可是魔法戒指
Yes, but magic rings?
不覺得聽起來非常詭異嗎
Does no part of this sound strange to you?
那得由你父親來決定
That's for your father to decide.
他聽都沒聽過 是要怎麼決定
Be hard for him to decide about a proposal he never hears.
重點就在這嗎
Is that what this is about?
對吧
It is, isn't it?
你寧願看着我們的山脈毀滅
You'd sooner let our entire mountain roast and rot,
也不願說一聲對不起
than have to say you were sorry.
你寧願讓全家人吃蟲子 也不願向他承認...
You'd sooner feed our family slugworms, than admit to him that you--
我沒有錯
I wasn't wrong.
我認同
I agree.
但你現在錯了
But you're wrong now.
我管他什麼魔法耳環
I don't care if they're magic earrings.
只要有一絲絲希望 不管聽起來多麼牽強
If there's even a hope of a solution here, no matter how farfetched,
我們的國王都應該要知道
our King needs to know about it.
要嘛你去跟你父親說 要嘛我去
Either you bring news of this to your father, or I will.
在卡扎督姆有句俗話說
There is a saying, in Khazad-d?m,
“滴水能穿石”
"The slow drip splits the boulder."
給他們一點時間
So give them time.
時間是我們最缺乏的奢侈品
And time is a luxury we lack.
萬一你的至高王發現...
Supposing your High King were to discover...
至高王怎麼樣
What about the High King?
算了 我不該說
No, I should not.
說什麼 快說
No. Say what? Speak plain.
你的至高王認爲 矮人不配擁有這種力量
Your High King believes the Dwarves to be unworthy of this power.
事實上 他禁止再打造任何戒指
In fact, he has forbidden the forging of any more Rings at all.
其實他根本不知道我在這裏
And the truth is he does not even know I am here.
這樣啊 我在自己的地盤上做什麼 跟他有什麼關係
Well. What business is it of his, how I conduct myself in my own realm?
–凱勒布林博... –我不管
- Celebrimbor-- - No!
無數生命危在旦夕
Countless lives are at risk.
我們沒時間耗費脣舌 說服他誰值得幫助
We have not the time to bandy words about, convincing him who is worthy of aid.
不過吉爾加拉德遲早會發現真相的
Nevertheless, sooner or later, Gil-galad will discover the truth.
如果沒有呢
Supposing he doesn't?
你要做什麼
What are you doing?
我要向至高王祝賀三戒的功效
I am congratulating the High King on the efficacy of The Three
告訴他我將關閉熔爐
and telling him that I am closing up the forge.
答應他我將盡快前往林頓會合
With a promise to join him in Lindon as soon as possible.
你要對至高王說謊
You would lie to your High King?
我是在爭取時間完成我們的使命
I would grant us the space to complete our work.
爲此我耗費了悠長歲月做準備
I have spent an age preparing for this.
成爲學徒 潛心鑽研
I have apprenticed, I have studied,
我的技藝已達顛峯
I have reached the very height of my craft.
這是屬於我的時刻
This... This is my moment.
他別想奪走
Now, he will not take it away.
抱歉...真的很抱歉
Sorry, sorry, sorry! I'm so sorry.
我以爲你是半獸人
I thought you were an Orc!
沒關係 不太痛
It's all right. Doesn't hurt. Oh!
不太痛 痛死了吧 我刺傷你的大腿
Doesn't hurt? Of course it hurts, I just stabbed you in the thigh!
還好啦
Could've been worse.
–來 我拔出來 –不要...
- Here, let me pull it out. - No, don't--
–不要拔出來比較好  –是嗎
- You're meant to leave it in! - Was I?
對 不管刺到哪 留着比較好
Yes! Whenever you're stabbed, you leave it in.
–我沒被刺過  –我也沒有
I've never been stabbed before! Neither have I!
你確定不痛
You sure it doesn't hurt?
這下真痛死了
No, now it hurts.
抱歉 我...
Sorry. I, uh...
來
Here.
好了 我來就好
No, stop. I'll do it.
我來吧
Let me.
我是艾絲翠
I'm Estrid.
伊熙爾杜
Isildur.
你是臭海人 你是要往山脊線去嗎
You're Sea-folk. Were you headed for the ridgeline?
倖存者會在紮營處等我們
The survivors will be waiting for us where we made camp.
還有我父親
My father, too.
你可能錯過他們了
I think you may have missed them.
你不瞭解我父親
You don't know my father.
你去過了 對吧
You've already been there, haven't you?
我也在找人
I was searchin' for someone too.
那裏只剩馬蹄印和爛泥巴
Nothin' left but hoofprints and mud.
不過呢 我發現這個
But... I found this.
這裏 標記了一條路
Here. And there's a path marked.
“佩拉基爾”
"Pelargir."
果然 父親沒有離開 他帶大家去了那裏
Of course. Father didn't leave, he led everyone there.
運氣好的話 你朋友也是
Your folk too, any luck.
佩拉基爾 努門諾爾舊聚落
港口沒看到半艘船
I didn't see any ships in the harbor.
保持希望
Keep hope.
誰知道會在那裏找到誰
There's no telling who we'll find down there.
你也在找家人嗎
You hoping to find kin as well?
我未婚夫
My betrothed.
別過去
Don't.
–怎麼回事  –半獸人
- What's happened? - Orcs.
我要去佩拉基爾 被他們攔截
Was on me way to Pelargir when they waylaid me.
–奪走了一切 –你還能行動嗎
- Took everything. - Can you travel?
你看看我
Look at me.
我們應該繼續前進
We ought to keep movin'.
至少給他一點吃的
Least we can do is give him something to eat.
艾絲翠 快走
Estrid, go!
抓好
Grab hold!
貝雷克
Berek!
你應該聽那女孩的話
You should've listened to the girl.
快走 上馬 我們走
Go! Get the horse. Get on. Go! Let's go.
救命
快走 壓低身子 快走
Move. Get down. Come on. Let's go. Come on. Come on.
謝謝
Thank you.
我是伊熙爾杜 還記得嗎
It's Isildur. Remember?
精靈的記憶不會黯淡
Elven memories do not dim.
這片森林裏 野人的數量是我們的好幾倍
Wildmen outnumber us many to one in these woods.
我的馬 我不能拋下它
My horse. I can't abandon him.
你想怎麼做就怎麼做吧
Settle your own affairs as seems you best.
我有我的事要忙
I have my own to attend to.
在佩拉基爾
In Pelargir.
什麼事
What affairs?
納維 跟國王報告...
Narvi, Narvi! Tell the King about the weans.
我們盡力了 我知道
We're doin' what we can. I see.
我們會盡全力
Well, we'll do what we can.
我知道
I know, I know.
納維 國王知道孩子們餓肚子嗎
Narvi, does the King know the children are hungry?
有點耐性
Have patience.
納維 拜託
Narvi, come on.
說實話 納維
Speak the truth, Narvi.
我現在就去跟國王報告
I'm speaking with the King now.
幫我們跟國王說
Speak to the King on our behalf.
納維
Narvi.
陛下 糧商們在外面
Sire. The food-merchants are outside.
他們來向您請願打開國家糧倉
Um, they're going to petition you to open the royal grain-reserves.
糧食儲備能撐多久
How long will the reserves last?
多數看法爲...三個月
By most accounts... Three months.
讓他們進來
Send them in.
陛下
Sire.
你可以走了
You can go.
凱勒布林博聲稱這些戒指 能帶給我們解決困境的力量
Celebrimbor claims these Rings will give us the power to solve our dilemma.
身爲矮人 我有責任告知你他的提議
I felt it my duty as a Dwarf to bring you his offer.
你要說的就是這些
Is that all you come to say?
不只
No.
還有呢
What else?
我是你的兒子
That I am your son.
我跟你一樣堅毅 一樣頑固
I'm hard as you, stubborn as you.
一樣一身傲氣 還有...
As crusted with pride. And, uh...
我錯了
I was wrong.
我不該不尊重你
I was wrong to disrespect you.
還有...
And...
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
你看起來很糟糕
You look terrible.
礦工的拳頭長滿了老繭
Miners have calloused fists.
揍人很痛
Their punches land hard.
等你小孩長大再來說痛
Wait till your children grow up.
父王...
Father, uh...
埃瑞吉安那種力量 我無法信任
this power in Eregion, I don't trust it.
你曾跟我說
You told me once,
精靈的命運是由 比我們更有智慧的存在決定的
the fate of Elves is decided by wiser minds than our own.
試圖扭轉 試圖逃避死亡
That to try and alter it, to try and cheat death,
可能會導致更大的災難
might lead to an even greater catastrophe.
我一直在想...
I keep wondering...
萬一你是對的呢
What if you were right?
這是你媽媽教你的嗎
Did your mother teach you how to do this?
發生什麼事
What happened?
你覺得呢
What d'you think happened?
我失敗了 我沒能阻止阿達爾 沒能...保護她
I failed. Failed to stop Adar. Failed... to protect her.
我以爲她會好起來
I thought she was getting better.
人類的肉體無法承受 半獸人邪箭腥臭的折磨
There is a foulness in Orc arrows not easily forgotten by human flesh.
見到你真好 伊熙爾杜
Pleases me to see you, Isildur.
經歷那場火山爆發的人 很少能撐到現在
So few who slept in the fire made it this far,
除了那些打上阿達爾印記的人
save those who took the Mark of Adar.
真希望能和你父親分享這份喜悅
I wish I could share my relief with your father.
他沒有拋下你
He did not abandon you.
努門諾爾會回來的
Númenor will return.
你和家人會再次團聚
Your family will be whole again.
幸好有你在
These people are fortunate you're here.
這村子需要治療師
This village needs a healer.
他們的治療師剛剛火葬了
Their healer just burned on a pyre.
你對貝烈瑞安德瞭解多少
What do you know of Beleriand?
精靈城 不是嗎
Elf-city, wasn't it?
那是一整個精靈王國
An entire Elf-realm.
我在那裏出生
I was born there.
如今它沉睡海底
Now, it lies under the wave.
貝烈瑞安德被毀後 我充滿憤怒
After it fell, I felt such anger.
對魔苟斯
Toward Morgoth.
但我最氣的是我自己
But I felt the most anger towards myself.
這是一種永遠無法平息的渴求 西奧
It is a thirst that can never be slaked, Theo.
最終會帶你走上毀滅之路
And in the end it will drink you dry.
好了 邊走邊弄
All right, yeah. More can do it in the same time, yeah.
你監視我們這麼多年
All those years you were watching us...
知道我父親嗎
d'you ever know my father?
不知道
No. I did not.
我也不知道
Neither did I.
但我很清楚 你不是他
But I know this much, he wasn't you.
我們之間曾有的關聯 現在也化爲灰燼
And anything you were to me, is ashes now.
我是覺得 我們沒必要再交談了
So for my part, we don't ever need to speak again.
好了啦 我沒辦法
小子 再拿點木頭來
Fetch me some more of that wood, lad.
對 那邊那堆
Yeah, from that pile there. Yeah.
這是以前的努門諾爾留下的
This is from old Númenor.
噴泉之類的 也不見噴半滴水
Some fountain. Barely spits a drop.
這不是噴泉 是引水道
It's not a fountain. It's an aqueduct.
用來把水引到家中
It's supposed to bring water into your homes.
人類蓋不出那種東西
Men can't build things like that.
在努門諾爾可以 你真該看看
In Númenor, we can. You should see it.
既然這麼厲害 你幹嘛離開
If it's so grand, why'd you leave?
聽說中洲有更厲害的
Heard there were grander things in Middle-earth.
你真想找回你的馬
D'you really want your horse back?
你知道它在哪
You know where he is?
今晚這裏見 月升之時
Meet me here. Tonight. Moonrise.
帶劍來
Bring a sword.
小心燒到自己
Don't burn yourself.
有你未婚夫的消息嗎
Any word of your intended?
沒有
No.
他會撐過來的 如果他有你一半堅強 我敢肯定
He'll make it. If he's even half as strong as you, I'm certain of it.
我沒你想的那麼堅強
I'm not so strong as you think.
很難不責怪自己
It's hard, not to blame myself.
責怪自己什麼
What for?
活下來
Being alive.
逃過一劫 太多人沒能活下來
For surviving. When so many others didn't.
我十歲時失去了母親
I was ten when I lost my mother.
我遊離岸邊太遠
Swam out further than I was supposed to.
被大浪捲走
Got caught in a riptide.
她淹死了
She drowned.
爲了救我
Saving my life.
在我媽...
After my mum--
我一直在想她現在過得怎樣
I keep wondering what it's like for her now.
有時我會在夢裏看到她
Sometimes, I see mine in dreams.
你好像已經接受事實了
You seem to have found peace with it.
沒有
No.
事實上 我剛跟你說的
The truth is, what I just told you,
在我家鄉沒人知道
back home, nobody knows.
我只告訴大家她淹死了
I just told them she drowned.
沒人知道是我害的
Nobody knows it was my fault.
從那時起我就覺得有義務
Ever since, I've felt bound.
要做出與衆不同的事
To try and do something singular.
特別的事
Something special.
要讓她的犧牲值得
To try and find a way to earn what she did.
我不知道要怎麼讓犧牲值得
I don't know if you can earn a thing like that.
我是覺得你只要接受 當作一份禮物
I think you just have to accept it, as a gift.
你對她來說很珍貴 所以她自願付出
One she gave freely because you were precious to her.
伊熙爾杜
Isildur.
這根本沒什麼肉
沒錯 要省着點吃 森林裏沒什麼東西可吃了
–陷阱常常什麼也沒抓到 –情況越來越糟了
–這根本吃不飽 –對啊
你也覺得冷吧
木材剩不多了 我知道我們需要...
卡斯柏剛剛在說 我在想 如果我們選對了
拜託今晚別下雨
冷死了
夠了 我們一整天沒吃東西了
你希望這次我們都生病
天殺的冷得跟小刀兒剌似的
看樣子 老鼠也有東西吃
–快好了 –讓開 小子
外面有人
Someone's out there.
只有我們偷來的馬 我再去讓它們安靜下來
Just them trotters we stole. I'll quiet 'em down again.
借一下火
Share your fire?
小鬼 你那麼晚在外面幹嘛
What are you doin' out here in the dark, boy?
找不到老媽
Lose your mum?
我是你們的夥伴
I'm one o' you.
我效忠阿達爾
I serve Adar.
那不是阿達爾的印記
That's not Adar's brand.
這證明我爲他做的比你們還多
It's proof I've done more for him than any of you can claim.
來看看
Try us.
看這傢伙吃得白白胖胖 肯定來自佩拉基爾
Look how well-fed he is. I'll wager this one comes from Pelargir.
你是來襲擊我們的嗎  就像你們對付其他人那樣
Are you here to attack us, lad? Same as your folk done the others?
我們從未襲擊你們
We've never attacked you.
你們襲擊我們三個營地
You attacked three of our camps.
抓住他
Hold him!
不要
No!
有埋伏
It's an ambush!
救命
Help!
伊熙爾杜
Isildur!
西奧
Theo! Theo!
撒謊女王
Queen of lies!
她不配治國
She's unfit to rule!
典禮上除了國王或女王的祈禱
No voice but the prayer of a king or a queen
不允許有任何聲音
is permitted during this ceremony.
然而
And yet...
努門諾爾的悲痛對我來說極爲神聖
the grief of Númenor is sacred to me.
你們的痛苦 就如同這國家的祈禱
Your pain, a prayer within these walls.
我聽到你們的悲傷 你們的憤怒
I hear your sorrow, and your anger.
我感同身受
I share it.
我們浴血奮戰 也被鮮血染紅
We have bloodied and been bloodied.
但要知道 我們會找到自己的方向
But know this... We will find our course.
如果我們當中還有人想發言
Should there be another among us who feels moved to speak...
先問問自己
firstly ask yourself this,
你爲了誰而哭泣
for whom do you cry out?
爲了我們已安葬之人
For those we have already buried?
爲了你的國家
For your kingdom?
還是爲了你自己
Or for yourself?
爲了伊熙爾杜
For Isildur.
在臨終之前 國王對我說
With his dying words, the King spoke to me,
說一切就是從這個開始 她聽取了建議
and said it was from this... she took counsel.
就因爲這樣 我們的親人枉死中洲
It is because of this, our kinsmen died in Middle-earth!
這顆精靈之石左右了你們的女王
This Elf-stone is your queen!
安靜
Silence!
一派胡言
Lies.
努門諾爾真正的統治者 絕不會聽信一介精靈神器
Númenor's true ruler would never place trust in an Elvish artifact.
拿去摧毀掉
Take it away and destroy it.
住手
No!
這顆帕藍提爾是我的
The palantír is mine.
我們需要它
We need it.
–精靈巫術  –殺人兇手
Elf sorcery! - Murderer!
撒謊女王
Queen of lies! Queen of lies!
–黑魔法  –女王
Dark magic! To the Queen.
–住手  –退後
Stop! Stop! Stand down.
彌瑞爾
Míriel!
–我的女王  –彌瑞爾
My Queen! Míriel!
救救我的女王
Save my Queen!
彌瑞爾
Míriel!
抓住我的手
Take my hand.
彌瑞爾
Míriel! Míriel!
法拉宗...
Pharaz?n! Pharaz?n! Pharaz?n! Pharaz?n!
大鷹選擇了法拉宗
The eagle favors Pharaz?n!
法拉宗...
Pharaz?n! Pharaz?n! Pharaz?n! Pharaz?n!